Finding Aid for D.C. Allen House of David Collection, 1795-1980
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
D.C. Allen House of David Collection 1795-1980 1903-1980
Allen, D. C., collector.
9997 Aa/2; mf 476c-mf480c
D. C. Allen was a Three Oaks, Michigan book dealer and collector of material on the House of David, an adventist cult founded in England. The leader of this cult was Benjamin Purnell who made Benton Harbor his home and the site of his follower’s business activities. The Allen collection (formerly housed at the Wyoming American Heritage Center) consists of most of the publications by and about the Israelite House of David, scattered manuscript materials mainly documenting the colony's business operations and court cases involving Purnell and the colony, and photographs and postcards depicting activities of the colony.
22 linear feet in 24 boxes
69 volumes
5 microfilms
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received from the University of Wyoming American Heritage Center (donor no. 9643 ) in September 2005. The materials had previously been given to the Center by Three Oaks, Mich., book dealer, D.C. Allen.
The collection is open to research.
D. C. Allen was a Three Oaks, Michigan book dealer, bibliographer, and collector of all kinds of materials relating to the House of David colony in Berrien Springs. Allen had the bookman's keen interest in the publications of Benjamin Purnell, the House of David, and the preceding Adventist messengers. For his catalog, Allen researched each pamphlet, monograph, and tract, creating note cards with information on publishing history and the importance of the item to House of David history. Allen sold his collection to the American Heritage Center in 1980 who subsequently transferred it to the Bentley Historical Library in 2005 when it was determined to be out-of-scope.
The Israelite House of David was established at Benton Harbor, Michigan, in 1903 by "King Benjamin" Purnell, a former roving preacher, and his wife Mary. In 1895, Purnell received a revelation that he was the "seventh messenger" described in the Book of Revelation. The previous six "angels" were Joanna Southcott, Richard Brothers, George Turner, William Shaw, John Wroe, and James Jezreel, all of England. As outlined in biblical scripture, the function of the seventh angel was to gather together the tribes of Israel prior to the second coming of Christ.
Incorporated under a religious charter, the Israelite House of David was a commonwealth with all possessions of members surrendered to Purnell who in turn provided for their support from a central fund which he administered. Most of the original members of the colony came from Indiana and Ohio, but this number increased dramatically following a trip to Australia in 1904-05 when Purnell appeared before the members of the previous messenger's followers, James Jezreel. During its heyday in the 1920s, the Benton Harbor colony numbered more than 900 members.
Activities of the colony included a farm, numerous commercial ventures including an amusement park, an open air tabernacle, a vegetarian restaurant, hotel, bands, crafts for sale in a gift shop, and a printing press. The colony was also remembered for its traveling baseball team with players' trademark braided long hair and beards.
Almost from its inception the colony and Purnell were the subject of both controversy and litigation. In 1923, some members of the colony brought suit against Purnell for the restitution of their property and wages for the time they had worked without pay. In another case, the people of the state of Michigan questioned the colony's tax exempt status for its many commercial ventures. Most damaging, Purnell was the subject of several morals charges. Just days before his death in December 1927, an order was issued to him to vacate the House of David premises and to dissolve the religious association.
Internal power struggles which began before Purnell's death culminated in a split in 1930 and the formation of a new colony, the Israelite House of David as Re-organized by Mary Purnell, later shortened to Mary's City of David, led by Purnell's widow Mary. The original colony which had earlier shortened its name to the House of David was led by Judge H. T. Dewhirst, the colony's chief secretary. In 1966, membership in the House of David numbered under 100, though some operations continued, such as the miniature train locomotive. The aging membership was still devout in their expectation of the imminent second coming.
Summary Contents List
Publications
Publications of the House of David -- Boxes 1-4 (part) and separately cataloged volumes
Publications of Mary's City of David -- Box 4 (part) and separately cataloged volumes
Writings about the House of David and City of David -- Box 4 (part) and separately cataloged volumes
Publications by and about Joanna Southcott (First messenger) -- Box 5 (part) and separately cataloged volumes
Publications by and about Richard Brothers (Second messenger) -- Box 5 (part) and separately cataloged volumes
Publications by and about George Turner (Third messenger) -- Separately cataloged volumes on shelf
Publications by and about John Wroe (Fifth messenger) and the Society of Christian Israelites (Christian Israelite Church) --B ox 5 (part) and separately cataloged volumes
Publications by and about James Jezreel (Sixth messenger) (New and Latter House of Israel) -- Box 5 (part) and separately cataloged volumes
Publications by and about Helen Barltrop (The Panacea Society) -- Separately cataloged volumes on shelf
Publications about British-Israelism -- Box 5 (part) and separately cataloged volumes
Publications by and about Richard W. Hill (follower and interpreter of Benjamin Purnell) -- Box 5 (part)
Esoteric and other writings of uncertain connection with the House of David or Southcottian prophets -- Box 5 (part) and separately cataloged volumes
Newspapers published by the House of David -- Boxes 6-8 and oversize folders
Newspapers published by the Mary's City of David -- Boxes 9-14
Manuscript Materials
Background/Biographical -- Box 15 (part)
Administrative Papers -- Box 15 (part)
Litigation -- Box 16
Scrapbooks -- Microfilm rolls, 1-5
Miscellaneous -- Boxes 17-18
Visual Materials
Photographs -- Boxes 19, 21-22
Postcards -- Box 20
Realia
Calendars and other artifacts -- Boxes 23-24
The collection gathered together by D. C. Allen includes published materials, manuscripts and other paper documentation, and photographs, postcards, and other visual materials. The published material consists mainly of books and pamphlets written by House of David founder "King Benjamin" Purnell and his wife Mary and others associated with the House of David. This collection was formerly stored at the University of Wyoming American Heritage Center.
Subjects:
Allen, D. C.; Cults--Michigan.; Baseball teams--Michigan--Benton Harbor.; Benton Harbor (Mich.)--Church history.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Benton Harbor.; House of David.; Mary's City of David.; Benton Harbor (Mich.)--History.; Purnell, Benjamin Franklin, 1861-1927.; Purnell, Mary Stollard, 1862?-1953.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Baseball--Michigan--Benton Harbor.; High Island (Mich.); Benton Harbor (Mich.); Business enterprises--Michigan--Benton Harbor.; Collective settlements--Michigan--Benton Harbor.; Buildings--Michigan--Benton Harbor.; Louis, Joe, 1914-1981.; House of David.; Mary's City of David.; Amusement parks--Michigan--Benton Harbor.; Miniature railroads--Michigan--Benton Harbor.; Purnell, Benjamin Franklin, 1861-1927.; Purnell, Mary Stollard, 1862?-1953.; Automobile dealerships--Michigan--Benton Harbor.; Ice industry--Michigan--Benton Harbor.
Contributors:
Allen, D. C.
Genre Terms:
Postcards.; Glass negatives.; Photographs.
- Publications
  The Publications, divided into several series, contains Allen's collection of books, pamphlets, and periodicals published by the House of David and by Mary's City of David. Also included are works about the House of David and publications by and about Joanna Southcott and the other Messengers preceding Benjamin Purnell in the House of David's understanding. The collection also includes a few other works, mainly dealing with esoteric knowledge, for which the connection to the House of David is unclear. For the ease of researchers, all other works in the Bentley Library's collection relating to the House of David have also been included in this inventory.
  Allen kept detailed notes on the sometimes confusing publication history of the House of David and City of David. His notecards are available in the Bentley Library Reading Room card file. Portions of his notes directly relating to editions and printings have been excerpted in this inventory. The cards often include additional information about the significance and meaning of the texts.
  The publications series is organized by publisher or subject: Publications of the House of David (sometimes called the Israelite House of David, including both the organization led by Mary and Benjamin Purnell before 1929 and the succeeding organization led by Judge Dewhirst after the split); Publications of Mary's City of David (initially known as the Israelite House of David as reorganized by Mary Purnell); Writings about the House of David and City of David; Publications by and about the six predecessor Messengers, Joanna Southcott, Richard Brothers, George Turner, William Shaw (no publications), John Wroe and the Society of Christian Israelites, and James Jezreel and the New and Latter House of Israel; Publications of Helen Barltrop (and the Panacea Society) and British Israelism (successors to Joanna Southcott not directly related to the House of David); Publications of Richard W. Hill (a follower and interpreter of Benjamin Purnell); Esoteric and other writings of uncertain connection with the House of David or other Southcottian prophets.
  Within each category, all titles are arranged in this inventory alphabetically by title. More substantial bound volumes are not located in the manuscript boxes, but should be retrieved by the call numbers listed for them.
  - Publications of the House of David
    - Aged script prophesies 7 angels will pour fire on beast of Armageddon (Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David [ 1917 ]) 8 p. (Box 1)
      [Allen annotation: Predictions by Brother Johannes, a sixteenth century French monk. Only a few copies were printed for members.]
    - Alphabetical index to Shiloh's messenger of wisdom (Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David [ 1926 ]) 70 p. (Volume FA 25 P985 A456)
      [Allen annotation: A dozen copies of this index were printed at the time of the state trial in 1926. About three copies were bound and the balance left in sewn sections. Most of this balance were destroyed in the print shop fire. This is one of the three copies that survived.]
    - Answers, and criticism of so called authors of booklet called Fall and rise of Man [Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David 1917 ] 31 p. (Box 1)
      [Allen annotation: Though presented as the work of an ex-colony member written in support of the teachings of the House of David it May be definitely credited to the pen of Benjamin. The pamphlet criticized was written by former members attempting to establish a rival colony (Golden Age Publishing Co.)]
    - The ascent to the mount of vision / Jane Lead [Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David 1932 ] 60 p. (Box 1)
    - [Benjamin's special song book] [Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David, c 1926 ] [32] p. (Box 1)
      [Allen annotation: 14 songs issued in a very small edition for members of the colony close to Benjamin.]
    - A bird's eye view of the conspiracy against the House of David [Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David 1924 ]) 16 p. (Box 1)
      [Allen annotation: Written by Judge Dewhirst. Printing of this pamphlet was not authorized by Benjamin and at the urging of attorney Wm. Barnard and others distribution was suppressed. It is likely that a very few copies escaped and were circulated but it must be considered quite rare.]
    - Book of dialogues 1st ed. (Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David 1912-1914 ), 5 volumes
      - Book 1 (Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David 1912 ) 126 p. (Box 1)
      - Book 2 (Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David 1912 ) 125 p. (Box 1)
      - Book 3 (Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David 1912 ) 127 p. (Box 1)
        [Allen annotation: Cover title underscored with red rules, tree type motifs on cover printed in red.]
      - Book 3 (Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David, [ 1914 ]) 127 p. (Box 1)
        [Allen annotation: Although marked "First edition" and dated 1912 this is in reality the 2nd edition. Cover title underscored with dark blue rules, tree motifs in blue and imprint set in different type.]
      - Book 4 (Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David 1913 ) 124 p. (Box 1)
      - Book 5 (Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David 1914 ) 125 p. (Box 1)
    - The book of Henoch the prophet, literally translated from the Ethiopic / by Richard Laurence, archbishop of Cashel, late professor of Hebrew in the University of Oxford. A reprint from an edition edited, with variations, and published by John Thomson, Glasgow, 1882 (Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David 1912 ) 112 p. (Box 1)
      [Allen annotation: The 1st House of David edition. Printed in blue ink with brown laid paper wraps. The cover title is within yellow and black ruled border. Cover title reads "The book of Enoch" Israelite House of David. The paper of the first edition is somewhat thinner than of the second.]
    - The book of Henoch the prophet, literally translated from the Ethiopic / by Richard Laurence, archbishop of Cashel, late professor of Hebrew in the University of Oxford. A reprint from an edition edited, with variations, and published by John Thomson, Glasgow, 1882 (Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David 1912 [i.e. 193-]) 110 p., 2 copies (Box 1)
      ([Allen annotation: 2nd House of David edition. The work was completely reset in different type. The wraps are brown leather grained paper. The wrapper title is within a single brown rule border. "Book of Enoch" House of David. Although still bearing the 1912 date, printing of this edition was not accomplished until the early 1930s and carries the Dewhirst imprint "House of David.".])
    - The book of Jasher: from Adam to the Flood (Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David, [ 1915 ]) 23 p. (Box 1)
      ([Allen annotation: 1st ed.])
    - The book of Jasher: from Adam to the Flood (Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David, [ 1917 ]) 23 p. (Box 1)
      [Allen annotation: 2nd ed.]
    - The book of Jasher: from Adam to the Flood (Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David, [ 1935 ]) 23 p., 4 copies Copies are, tan, blue, two shades of green (Box 1)
      [(Allen annotation: 3rd ed. The issue in tan, leather grained wraps May have priority. There is another issue of this second [sic] printing recognizable by its green wraps and a third issue in blue wraps.]
    - "Book of life." Open "In the hand of the angel."--Rev. 10:2 "The word of God." Rev. 19:13 "The everlasting gospel."--Rev. 14:6 ... A message addressed to the twelve tribes of Israel scattered abroad greeting ([Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David 1903 ]) 20 p., 2 copies (Box 1)
      (1 copy is a photocopy with slightly different pagination. Title revised in mss. to read: The little book of life [Allen annotation: Without doubt the earliest printing for the colony at Benton Harbor though quite likely not printed by the colony.])
    - A book of remembrance (Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David, c 1931 )
      (Cover title: The what? where? when? why? and how? of the House of David.)
      BHL holdings according to Allen publishing history, with Allen annotations:
      - 1st edition (Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David 1931 ) 33 p., Green and gilt pictorial wraps, portrait. (Box 1)
      - 2nd edition, 1st issue. (Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David) 32 p., Portrait and 9 illustrations but the wraps are the same as the 1st edition. (Box 1)
      - 2nd edition, 2nd issue (Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David 1935 ? ) 32 p., Differing from the 1st edition only in the style of wraps and lacking three of the illustrations printed in the 1st edition. (Box 1)
      - 2nd edition variant, Not described by Allen. Different style of wraps. (Box 1)
      - 3rd edition (Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David 1938 ?) 32 p. (Box 1)
        (Considerably revised with additional information on the cold storage plant built in 1937. Six of the plates and illustrations have been deleted. Typographical error on page 17, line 30.)
      - Reprint ( 1950 ) 32 p., [Reprint of 3rd edition with typographical errors on page 17 corrected.] (with differing styles of wraps) (Box 1)
      - Later revision (Benton Harbor, Mich.: House of David, after 1960 ) 31 p.
        [Appears to be a late-20th-century revision.]
    - Book of rules (Box 1)
      (see Rules and regulations for the kingdom of God's sake)
    - The book of wisdom (Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David, [ 1904- ])
      [Allen annotation: The Books of wisdom were the second of Benjamin's divine writings and were second only to the "Star of Bethlehem" in importance. While the message of the Star is, for the most part, aimed at the followers of the previous messengers, the Books of wisdom are a basic introduction and catechism of the Israelite faith.]
      (BHL note: The Book of wisdom was issued first as a single volume of 64 pages in 1904. The BHL collection does not include a copy of the 1904 volume. The book was Expanded to four volumes of 64 pages in 1905. The BHL collections includes only books two and three. In 1908 the fire in the print shop destroyed the stock and plates. The set then was revised to 100 pages and extended to five volumes. In 1912 the set was further expanded to its final form with the printing of the sixth and seventh volumes. In its final form the first six volumes contain a prefatory message titled "Images and likenesses" signed by Mary and Benjamin. After the division in 1930 those copies remaining in stock were subjected to a symbolic erasure of Mary's name.)
      - Original Printing
        - Book 2. 64 p., The wraps are pale blue. The cover title is within a single thin rule border. The trumpet insignia is the early simple form. There is no frontis, preface or the preliminary article "Images and likenesses." The only other publication offered for sale is the Star obtainable from "Mary and Benjamin or the House of David." The text is printed in blue ink. No title page, cover and caption title only. (Box 1)
        - Book 3. 64 p., Similar to Book 2, wraps are red. (Box 1)
      - Circa 1910 printing
        - Book 1, blue wraps, no portrait, no prelims, no publication list (Box 1)
        - Book 2, Pale brick orange wraps, thin, thick rule surrounding cover title, no publication list. Type 1 portrait of Benjamin. Text printed in blue ink. There is no imprint on the wrapper. (Box 1)
        - Book 3, 2 copies Cover title within thin, thick rule, wraps ivory colored. No publication list. Type 1 portrait of Benjamin. Lack of cover imprint corrected by rubber stamping 1st leaf. Text printed in blue ink. A few copies were issued in wraps intended for Book 1 (Box 1)
        - Book 4, 2 copies Cover title within thin, thick rules. Type 1 frontis portrait of Benjamin. Some copies lack cover imprint which has been corrected by rubber stamping the first leaf. Text printed in blue ink. (Box 1)
        - Book 5, Cover title within thin, thick rules. Wraps very pale blue color. No imprint on cover. Copies with type 1 and type 2 portrait. Text printed in blue ink. (Box 1)
      - Circa 1912 printing
        - Book 6 [1st edition.], 2 copies Cover title within thin, thick rules, type 1 frontis portrait of Benjamin. Blue wraps. Text printed in blue ink. (Box 1)
        - Book 7 [1st edition.], Cover title within thin, thick rules. Type 1 frontis portrait of Benjamin. Text printed in blue ink. (Box 1)
      - Circa 1913 printing
        (BHL note: In the publication list only the first four Dialogue books are offered. It seems logical to assume that this issue was prior to 1914 when the 5th Book of dialogues was issued but must date 1912 or after when the first four Dialogue books were issued. Copies without the literature list were for the membership.])
        - Book 1, 2 copies The wraps are red, cover title within thin, thick rules. Type 1 frontis portrait. The text is printed in blue ink. (Box 1)
        - Book 4, Cover title within thin, thick, thin rules, type 2 frontis portrait of Benjamin. 4 Dialogue books offered. Ball of fire not offered. Wraps pale blue. Some copies have type 1 portrait.
      - Circa 1914 printing
        - Book 1, Red wraps. Cover title within thin, thick, thin rules. Type 2 frontis portrait. Text printed in blue. (Box 1)
          (Issued in 1914 on basis of publication list.)
      - Circa 1916 printing
        - Book 6, 2 copies [Cover title within thin, thick, thin rules. Blue wraps. Type 3 frontis portrait of Benjamin. Ball of fire vol. 1 and 2 offered in publication list. Text printed in black ink. On later printings the Israelite House of David imprint has been altered to read House of David.] (Box 1)
        - Book 7 [2nd edition]., 4 copies [Cover title within thin, thick, thin rules. Blue gray wraps. Type 4 frontis portrait of Benjamin. Text printed in black ink. In later printings the Israelite House of David imprint has been altered to read House of David.] (Box 1)
      - Circa 1917 printing (Box 1)
        - Book 1, [White wraps with three color cuts of flag and eagle. Trumpet insignia printed in red. Wrapper title within a border of chain links. Text printed in black ink. Type 2 frontis portrait.]
        - Book 1, 2 copies [Pink wraps with two color cut of flag and eagle. Trumpet insignia printed in red. Wrapper title within equal size rules. Type 4 frontis portrait. Text printed in flack ink. A later is sue has the wrapper title within thick, thin rules and the wrapper with the flag and eagle cut is printed in one color. Text printed in black ink. Type 4 frontis portrait.] (Box 1)
        - Book 5, 2 copies [Cover title within thin, thick, thin rules. Very pale blue color. Type 2 frontis portrait of Benjamin. Ball of fire, etc., offered in publication list. Text printed in black ink.] (Box 1)
      - Circa 1918 printing
        - Book 1, 2 copies [Pink wraps, cover printed in one color. Thick thin ruled border.] (Box 1)
        - Book 2, 2 copies [Darker orange wraps, cover title within thin, thick, thin rules. Publication list offers Ball of fire, Books of poetry, Eden paradisiacal liberty. Type 4 portrait. Text printed in black ink.] (Box 1)
      - 1970 printing
        - Book 2, [Photo offset reprint] (Box 1)
        - Book 3, [Photo offset reprint] (Box 1)
        - Book 4, 2 copies [Photo offset reprint] (Box 1)
        - Book 5, 2 copies [Photo offset reprint] (Box 1)
      - Unidentified printing
        - Book 2, [appears to be photo offset reprint] (Box 1)
        - Book 3, [appears to be photo offset reprint] (Box 1)
    - The book of wisdom (Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David, [ 1904- ], 6 volumes (Box 1)
      Books 1-6 [Allen annotation: Various issues. This set belonged to Bessie Daniels who betrayed Benjamin Purnell to the police in 1927.]
    - Brief concordance to the Star of Bethlehem (Benton Harbor, Mich.: Israelite House of David, [ 1910 ?] ) 158 p. (Box 1)